well hello today I'd like to tell you
about Neil postman's amusing ourselves
to death
this is a fun little book The subtitle
is public discourse in the age of Show
Business
and it's got an introduction by his son
Andrew Postman
so the book came out in 1983 and I think
the obvious question you might very well
ask yourself is well what does that book
have to say to me today
well a lot as it turns out so hopefully
I'll get into some of that so what the
book explores actually is the impact of
electronic media on a Democratic Society
in 1983 the primary Electronic media was
television yes there was radio but you
know television had pretty much taken
over
um so you might very well yeah again
what's that have to do with today well
we still have television but we have a
lot more media including the medium
through which you're watching me
this isn't television this is YouTube
it's not real life
I'm performing
I am babbling because it's past eight
o'clock so that's a problem with this
that television would edited that out
but I don't care I'm just going to keep
going so you're going to soon learn that
the tools of Television actually follow
us into our modern world of cell phones
and social media
and it does more actually
Back Then There Were portable
televisions my mother had one it was
I don't know about that wide about this
deep about this tall
black and white and toward the end you
kind of had to pound on it to get the
picture to show up on the screen instead
of snow because there was something
loose inside
but uh now
we've got our portable little
distractions with us all the time unless
you're like me and leave it in your bag
and don't care in your pocket
which horrifies my students especially
if it's quiet and they're taking a test
and they hear you know I don't have the
alarm on or anything I have all I have
it on silent mode but it does vibrate if
I get a text or I get a call and they're
like aren't you gonna check see who it
is nope
3 15 then I'll check when school's out
and then I usually forgotten by then
so a classic story about the power of
electronic media which the book does
talk about
is the Kennedy versus Nixon debate of
the 1960 presidential election Nixon at
the time was vice president for outgoing
president Dwight Eisenhower and he had
already used the power of Television for
his famous Checkers speech in which he
claimed he was not a crook and that oh
we did get one gift and he pulls up a
puppy and we're keeping him
puppy looked terrified
Nixon did not present well on TV he was
awkward
it actually in his seventh 1972
presidential campaign he tried to put on
a more informal demeanor as a man of the
people when he ran for reelection
so his people arranged a photo shoot of
him taking a casual stroll on the beach
of San Clemente California
and it backfired us he insisted on
wearing his black wingtips
on the beach
with the surf watching in and out and
the sand
so this is the man who went up against
John Kennedy in the 1960 election and
the first televised presidential debate
now after the debate
pollsters found an interesting dichotomy
those who listened to on the radio felt
that Nixon had won the debate
those who watched on television felt
Kennedy had won
now think about it for a minute
the visual Dimension does nothing here
but think about what I've done here I've
got a carefully crafted set I've got a
light on in the back serves absolutely
no purpose to this
it's just a light on in the back to make
the set more three-dimensional I have a
lava lamp up there somewhere I think I'm
pointing at it just to provide a little
bit of motion but not to be the weird
garish motion of
this light which I absolutely adore but
makes some of you crazy if I use it
um and I've carefully set up some lights
off screen here to evenly light my face
to make myself look pretty and I have
enough separation from my background so
we've got just the hint of background
blur so uh
I can make myself all pretty and stuff
for a
very very small Channel on YouTube
um
but I thought through all that
for the visual medium
you know my driving videos I just get up
to my microphone like this and talk into
it and I sound good and I just brought
that North Dakota scenery run and I
could just do a podcast I don't even
have to have that North Dakota scenery
it doesn't matter
radio you have to imagine
so uh
so let's talk about the visual Dimension
there mixin arrived to this debate
exhausted because he'd been sick and he
was dealing with some health issues
Kennedy was arrived well rested and well
practiced because he locked himself in a
hotel room and practiced over and over
again
Kennedy looked at and addressed the
camera like I'm doing to you
except when I looked down at my notes
because I'm too lazy to or and too cheap
to buy uh a teleprompter was because
some YouTubers use teleprompters not me
uh Nixon looked off camera to address
the various reporters
which looks really awkward when you're
viewers are there
Kennedy was tanned and healthy looking
Nixon was pale and he had kind of the
same problem I do fast growing stubble
uh to cover his stubble Nixon wore lazy
shave a drugstore pancake makeup
which is as awful as it sounds under the
hot studio lights because there were no
LED lights like I have here
uh under the hot studio lights he
started to sweat and the makeup just
melted away leaving visible beads of
sweat
uh and of course black and white he's
wearing a light gray suit and it just
Blended in with the background
uh Kennedy was smart enough to wear or
at least aware enough I should say or
had good advisors to wear a dark suit
that's contrasted better
I don't think I'm contrasting well with
my background but moving on
so anyway as Nixon later observed
a picture is worth a thousand words
and this shows the power of the visual
media to sway opinion so Neil Postman of
course he talks about this but he goes a
lot further than this He suggests a sort
of golden age of the written word
you know before radio even
compare the Lincoln Douglas debates to
Modern presidential debates now Neil
Postman died before the
2016-2015 election does anybody remember
Marco Rubio in the Republican primary
debates
and Donald Trump bringing penis size
into the Republican primary
uh yep
penis size is important in picking out a
president
uh you know we got all these middle-aged
and elderly men
I am just worried about what's hanging
between their legs
so the level of discourse in the Lincoln
Douglas debates is quite a contrast
um no penis sizes in sight
these are actually very lengthy
arguments although not recorded worth
noting except in writing they're very
lengthy arguments with plenty of
research and literary references nothing
like the sound bite oriented debates of
today and a lot longer
uh no one would watch these today
they're boring but consider the time in
which they take place
what do you have for entertainment you
don't have music you don't have TV you
don't have radio you don't have internet
and even books are kind of tough to get
hold of
and life is a lot of work so they're
almost a welcome entertainment
so why aren't debates like this
so I'm recording this in 2022 I've seen
debates where discuss inflation you have
15 seconds go and then they ring the
bell at the end of the 15 seconds
what what am I going to say in 15
seconds absolutely nothing
I hate those kind of debates at the same
time you don't want them going on at
length and uh
saying nonsense it'll be nice if they'd
answer the questions
honestly not try to beat around them not
try to avoid them
and just be direct
but can't work that way
and you know instead of going for the
sound bite let's go for some lengthy
policy what are we going to do and not
the shouting over each other
interrupting each other because my God
that first debate between Trump and
Biden I just wanted to drop kick both of
them that was awful
so
um I would just add uh read older books
versus those of today the older books
take a lot longer to get going and
readers went along with it
today books have to compete with the
spectacle of television or movies
they need to sorry they need to grab
attention right away
and what we're seeing as a result
is a reduction in attention spans
consider what television and now the
internet do yes they can bring some
powerful pieces and information to us
but they also bring us a whole lot of
nonsense and misinformation and they are
Geared for the most part toward a short
attention span
what is Tick Tock I hate tick tock
uh certainly it contains good stuff I'm
sure
don't I don't go on it but I'm sure it
does
but a lot of it is just ephemera and
meaningless just uh let's dance to this
funky music and be all woogle wiggah and
get the beat going
yeah
great
um or Twitter
how do you lay out an intelligent
thought in 140 characters
look at television
try to watch a lot of what you grew up
with especially if you're a little older
like me
um a lot of it just seems so silly now
and yes there is some good stuff that
was made back then
and we're going to look back on a lot of
what's being made now and say yep
and yet there's good stuff being made
right now
so I grew up when cable was kind of in
its infancy most television was just a
few networks that you would pick up with
rabbit ears or if you were more rural a
big antenna mounted on your roof or on a
tower somewhere
um
and you watched whatever they put up
Phillips bleeps and blunders which was a
real show
Hollywood Squares The Price is Right
Growing Pains Alice and a lot of it was
silly
and totally forgettable once in a while
you'd get a very special episode that
tried to dive deeper but always in a
very superficial way
nothing messy all sewn up in 30 minutes
with carefully timed commercial breaks
and what about the good stuff
laughs
so this isn't an example of the good
stuff
uh Down Below in the video description I
have a link to an example of public
discourse on important issues
atheist blogger hemant meta and
televangelist Tony Perkins came on Fox
News to discuss a Pew research finding
that faith and spirituality rank forth
in where Americans Find meaning in life
I don't have a problem with that I I
think a preacher and a atheist who have
very different World Views might spark
some interesting conversation
if we're after conversation
but they only get a few minutes to do
that and then
after three minutes and 36 seconds
that includes the anchor diving into The
Fray
we switched to sex and gender
two people
an atheist blogger and a televangelist
what the hell do they know about sex and
gender neither one's a biologist neither
one's a psychologist neither one's an
evolutionary biologist
they are not experts and yet here we go
so we get the remaining two minutes to
discuss this
three minutes and 36 seconds to discuss
Faith among Americans and why it's
Fourth
and then we jump to sex and gender for
two minutes
what a vapid waste of time
where absolutely nothing is accomplished
uh very shallow we get a few sound bites
of very clearly biased anchor and we can
pretend like we got a deep discussion of
two issues
but
it was absolutely nothing
and
the wrong people discussing it and you
know to his credit at least haven't meta
admitted that hey we're probably not the
right people to be having this
discussion
preacher just dove in anyway
I got God on my side so I know
so uh had Neil Postman lived to see the
president he could have seen the rise of
the meme as discussion
never mind of delving into the
complexity and the nuance and all the
gray in an argument show them an image
and a pithy phrase that's enough
and for all the problems compare the
presidential debates of 1960 to those of
today
it's even set aside penis size because I
hope to God that's the only time in my
life that gets brought up in a
presidential debate or any debate ever
uh Republicans Democrats like I said
earlier were horrified by the first
debate
we all agreed on that
but we turn it all into spectacle and
entertainment
I'm told to be entertaining as a teacher
learning is boring
so better to whip out the entertainment
device in the topic
the written word can be trite or silly
but it is also open to deeper analysis
and discussion and more importantly
requires an active contribution from the
reader
it's really easy to turn on an audiobook
and get out your cell phone and just be
like
oh chapter's over
I wonder what that was about
um
so the electronic media definitely
thrive on emotion not deep analysis and
what Postman was really lamenting is the
loss of this depth and Analysis in our
own culture
any of you watched Doctor Who
I started watching that back in the 80s
I've watched a lot of the 1960s stuff
all the way to the present day I'll
admit I'm kind of light on a lot of the
present day stuff but I do know who the
current doctor is it's a woman
don't know her name but she's a woman
well she doesn't have a name because
it's Doctor Who and we don't actually
call her doctor who she just call her
the doctor so there we go I don't have
to know her name but anyway
it's it's actually a silly BBC show for
children it's originally meant to be
educational they're supposed to have you
know one week would be history the next
week would be science and whatever but
uh
compare the cultural references of the
new and the old the original version has
references to Shakespeare and other
classical literature the new version has
I ain't afraid to know ghosts which is a
Ghostbusters references for those of you
who are luddites
and to be fair the new version had a
Shakespeare episode
and the cast high-five each other when
they find out the Shakespeare is
bisexual
cause yeah
that's the important thing about him who
we think this man who's been dead for
multiple centuries slept with not his
clever writing not his insights on
Humanity
what he does with his genitals
so we know the power of books Postman
brings up the power of gutenberg's
printing press
uh I got to do a driving video one of
these days about a guy who was burned at
the stake for the crime of translating
the Bible into English
um and with a book you hold the wisdom
of humanity in your hand
or go on Twitter see if Justin Bieber
flashed his butt again
um now I have melded the present a bit
here with Mr postman's book because it
truly is a Timeless book
uh the big idea is that electronic media
substitute entertainment for thought and
spectacle and emotion take over
we focus on social issues
not the big issues for our time that
will impact us for Generations
why do you think there's such a focus on
transgender and gay people right now
gets people mad
that's it
Evolution isn't working anymore so we
gotta dig up something new let's go
after a different group oh we can't it's
really not acceptable going after racial
groups anymore yeah we'll just go after
sexual minorities but the important
thing is there it's a distraction
from serious issues
oh can't afford health care
wait two men are getting married over
there
um Postman was definitely prescient it's
far worse than television and so much
more banal
uh kids sit in class worried about their
streaks on Snapchat when I grew up
streaks was totally different
meaning
and you can look that what streaking is
up I won't get into that they're worried
about their streaks on chat snapchat
they're they're meaningless texts silly
games and you know forget anything
deeper and yeah I know they're kids
so what really scares me is the adults
that are so distracted
so Postman saw this and really
it's an atlas Huxley type of future
Atlas Huxley wrote Brave New World
and one of the big things in Brave New
World is people are just so sorry so
distracted by all the entertainment and
other things
that they don't worry about the fact
that they're living under a totalitarian
government
and that may be what we're headed toward
now
so on that happy note I want to thank
you for watching
and uh let me know if you've read Neil
postman's book have you read any other
good works on
the rise of social media
let us know that maybe there's some good
in it I don't know let us know down in
the comments so uh thank you for
watching
we'll talk to you later
bye-bye